<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Helps to the assurance of God's love whereby a true believer may with the help of Gods good spirit know that he had a being in the love of God before he had a being in the world : to which is added a spiritual touch-stone for the tryal of the sincerity of our love to God / by Samuel Pack.</title>
            <author>Pack, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54342</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P150</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26175</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09378697</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09378697</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42902</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54342)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42902)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1313:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Helps to the assurance of God's love whereby a true believer may with the help of Gods good spirit know that he had a being in the love of God before he had a being in the world : to which is added a spiritual touch-stone for the tryal of the sincerity of our love to God / by Samuel Pack.</title>
                  <author>Pack, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>69 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.M. for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Love.</term>
               <term>God --  Worship and love.</term>
               <term>Love --  Religious aspects.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42902:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42902:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Helps to the ASSURANCE OF GOD'S LOVE: Whereby a true Believer may, with the help of Gods good Spirit, know that he had a Being in the Love of God before he had a Being in the World.</p>
            <p>To which is Added, A ſpiritual Touch-ſtone for the tryal of the Sincerity of our Love to God.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Pack</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. M.</hi> for the Author, 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:42902:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42902:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe ſenſe of Gods love is that which is a Saints Heaven here in its inchoation, and ſhall be their Heaven hereafter in its Conſummation. The more thou haſt of the clear diſcoveries of Gods love in thy heart: The more wilt thou be (from thy heart) diſcovering thy love to the God of Love; The brighter the love of God doth ſhine in thy Soul (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thy ſins committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this loveing God, the more will
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42902:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>thy heart burn againſt thy Sins which thou haſt committed againſt this God of love; the deeper draught thou haſt of the aſſurance of Gods everlaſting love to thee the more will the waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> even the bitter waters of affliction be ſweetned unto thee; the more thy heart is lifted up in contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of that fulneſs of comfort and joy which the God of love, in the riches of his love hath laid up for thee in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother world, the more wilt thou be lifted up above and weaned from an inordinate love unto, or delight and complacency in the inticeing vanities of this world; and foramuch as this love of God in Chriſt is that ſea and ſun, that mine and fountain from whence through Chriſt we are Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of thoſe Glorious Priviledges of Election by God, peace with God together with adoption, perſeverance, and an intereſt in the new Covenant, which contains in the Bowells thereof Effectual calling and Pardon of Sin
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42902:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>and a participation of the Spirit in all his ſaveing influential operations, I have therefore I ſay in the firſt place laid down <hi>12</hi> characters of Gods love to believers. And now, Reader, I have given thee a hint of that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſequel of this diſcourſe, I think it not amiſſe to diſcover to thee the occaſion of the Publiſhing theſe few ſheets, which is firſt from ſome fears and Jealouſies that are upon my Spirit, that God is comeing in ſome cloudy diſpenſation;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.1.</note> And when God ſhall be pleaſed thus to wrap himſelf up in a cloud, Then nothing will comfort a child of God like the ſhining face of of Gods love in Chriſt, and an inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in that Rainbow of his Covenant, in which Covenant he hath made over himſelf in all his Attributes, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection &amp; Conſolation in a day of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al: Another cauſe of my Publiſhing theſe lines is the miſtakes that are both in the wicked and the Godly about their intereſt in the love of God,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42902:4"/>wicked men they ground their hopes of an intereſt in Gods-love upon their outward injoyments, becauſe they Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper in the world, and all things go well with them as to their outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns; which outward Proſperity is ſo far from being an evidence of Gods Everlaſting love, that it is rather (being unſanctified) a ſigne of his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and diſpleaſure; and as for Gods people they are under a great miſtake on the other hand, apprehending their outward afflictions, to be ſignes of Gods hatred and diſpleaſure, whereas thoſe outward afflictions (being San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified) are ſigns of Gods everlaſting love; now for the ſakes of ſuch afflicted <hi>Jobs</hi> who under bitter trials are ready to cry out he counteth me for his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, I have undertook this work, that they may drink thoſe waters of <hi>Marah</hi> with more comfort; when they know that theſe afflictions are laid on them by one that hath an everlaſting love towards them. The laſt reaſon of my
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42902:4"/>Publiſhing thoſe evidences of Gods love, and Election, and Adoption, is not (I hope) becauſe I would be in Print; neither becauſe I look upon theſe Sermons to be more worth, than other Sermons that are never like to come to the preſſe; but becauſe ſeveral Precious Souls that heard me, when I did Preach upon thoſe words in the <hi>1 Epheſians</hi> the latter part of the <hi>3 verſe, Who hath bleſſed us with all Spiritual bleſſings in heavenly things in Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>) did earneſtly deſire me to write them out thoſe uſes of trial or examination, whereby they might be aſſured, that they had an intereſt in thoſe ſpiritual bleſſings in heavenly things in Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which we then reduced to theſe <hi>12</hi> heads: <hi>1.</hi> the Love of God, <hi>2.</hi> Election, <hi>3.</hi> Adoption, <hi>4.</hi> an Intereſt in the New Covenant, <hi>5.</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual wiſdom, <hi>6.</hi> Perſeverance in grace <hi>7.</hi> Pardon of Sin, <hi>8.</hi> Sanctification of our Nature; <hi>9.</hi> Juſtification, of our Perſons, <hi>10.</hi> the Acceptation of our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42902:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>11.</hi> Supportation under and Conſolation in our Sufferings, <hi>12.</hi> Glorification. And as I handled theſe Particulars before mentioned, I laid down ſome trials where we might know, whether thoſe Spiritual bleſſings in heavenly things in Chriſt, were ours, and ſeeing God is ſo ready to fulfill the deſires of them that fear him; I think it is our duties in our Places, to lay out our ſelves to the utmoſt of our abilities to fulfill the deſires of Gods People; eſpecially when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that which may conduce to the honour of God and the good of their precious Souls: what is it that brings more honour unto the God of Heaven, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> holy, the humble, and chearful walking of his people while they are here on earth? and what is it that will cauſe a believer, to be more holy, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and cheereful, than to know that he hath an intereſt in thoſe ſpiritual bleſſings which are more worth than <hi>10000</hi> worlds? Now that Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42902:5"/>may know that they are inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted in thoſe ſpiritual bleſſings, I have laid down many trials to evidence our intereſts in each of them, that ſo if a believer cannot experience one trial he may experience another, and if thoſe poor labours of mine do find as good acceptance with thee, now they are in thine eyes, as they did with the people of God when they had them in their ears, I ſhall be the more Incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, to Publiſh the evidences of our intereſt in thoſe other ſpiritual bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings which we have before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And if thou gaineſt any Comfort by my Poor endeavours, let God have the glory from whom Proceeds every good and perfect gift; and let the Poor Penman be a ſharer in thy pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, who is thy ſervant for Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Samuel Pack.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42902:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:42902:6"/>
            <head>Twelve Diſcriminating Characters.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Whereby</hi> A poor Mourner in <hi>Sion,</hi> for want of the Evidences of Gods Love, may know that he had a being in the love of God, before he had a being in the World.</head>
            <p n="1">1. IF thou art one that canſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thy ſelf, that thou haſt an Intereſt in the Love of God, thou art one that haſt in experimental Knowledge of this God of Love. If thou art one that haſt a Practical obediential Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edge of God, then thou mayeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omfortably and upon good grounds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, that God loves thee; but it is not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42902:7"/>every Knowledge of God that will Characterize a perſon to be an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Gods love; for if we look into 1 <hi>Rom.</hi> 21. we may ſee that there were ſome that had a rational con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed Knowledge of God in the book of the Creatures; and yet we ſee in the latter end of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they did ruſh into the greateſt Abominations imaginable. A Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God in the book of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (only) will not keep the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from committing the greateſt ſins againſt God; But thou that wouldſt Know upon ſure grounds that God loves thee, ſee if thou doeſt know God in his power, as to Fear him; in his Mercy, as to Love him, and his faithfulneſs to believe him. And if all the Attributes of God have ſuch an influence upon thee, then I dare tell thee for thy comfort, that thou mayſt aſſure thy ſelf that God Loves thee: For Chriſt who is Truth it ſelf, ſayth, <hi>John.</hi> 10.14.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42902:7"/>That thoſe ſheep of his whom he knows with a Knowledge of Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, they know him with a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Love and Obedience: But if thou art one that doeſt not fear God for his Greatneſs, nor love him for his Goodneſs, nor believe him for his Faithfulneſs; but in ſtraits and troubles, canſt allow thy ſelf in taking indirect courſes with <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ahaziah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.7. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.2.</note> it is a ſign thou haſt at (Preſent) but little grounds to hope that thou art an object of Gods Love.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thou that wouldeſt know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou canſt aſſure thy ſelf of the Love of God, examine thy ſelf whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou haſt received from God thoſe peculiar favours, which he doth give only to thoſe who are the objects of his Love. Now there are ſpecial favours which God beſtowes only on his own peculiar people:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.19.20.36.25, 26, 27.</note> Thoſe ſpecial favours are <hi>A new Heart, and a new Spirit; an heart of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42902:8"/>Fleſh, a ſaveing knowledge of himſelf; a ſelf-loathing for Sin, and an enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned underſtanding, &amp; the fear of God, and Love to God, and Sincerity before God, and all the gifts and graces of the Spirit of God.</hi> Now theſe are the ſpecial favours which God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowes only on thoſe that are the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of his Love. Oh my friends, take heed you do not build your hopes of Intereſt in Gods love upon the ſandy foundations of outward in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments. Many are ready to look upon their outward injoyments, as Health &amp; Strength, Peace, and Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the bleſſing of God on their outward injoyments to be infallible ſigns of Gods love; whereas indeed thoſe outward things are many times inſtead of being ſigns of Gods Love (being Unſanctified and Miſimpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) are ſigns of Gods Reprobateing anger. But if God have beſtowed thoſe other favours upon thee before mentioned, then thou mayſt be ſure
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42902:8"/>that God Loves thee. The Love of God doth in a providential way extend it ſelf to all his Creatures; But his everlaſting Love, and his choyceſt and endeared affections, theſe amongſt the ſonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Adam,</hi> are only partakers of, to whom God hath given a <hi>new Heart,</hi> and ſuch a practical Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of himſelf, together with all the gifts and graces of his Spirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If thou art one that canſt upon good grounds aſſure thy ſelf that thou art an object of Gods Love, then this Love of God hath been of an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive nature to draw thee to all thy Dutys both Relative and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as we have it in <hi>Jeremiah.</hi> 31.3. <hi>I have loved thee with an Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love; therefore with loving Kindneſs have I drawn thee.</hi> My friends, I beſeech you try what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence the Love of God hath upon your Hearts, in the drawing of you to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe duties, which are the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42902:9"/>to corrupt nature; and the moſt loathſome to the fleſh: After that Chriſt had manifeſted his love to <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus,</hi> and told him that Salvation was come to his houſe, then he could take ſhame to himſelf, in the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of his Extortion. If thou canſt aſſure thy ſelf of the Love of God, then the Glory of the God of Love will be thy ultimate End in all thy duties; And when thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveſt pride, or ſelf, or vain-glory creeping into thy duties, oh how is thy ſoul perplexed and diſturbed. But on the contrary, if thou art one that doeſt that which is thy duty, but art drawn thereto by wicked ends, thou haſt but little grounds to aſſure thy ſelf that thou art in the Love of God; If thou art converſant in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious duties, towards God, or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity towards men; and art drawn thereto by Phariſaical vain-glorious ends; It is then high time for thee to look about thee, for that hopes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42902:9"/>thou haſt of the Love of God, is but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deluſion of the Devil; therefore ſee if it be Love to God, that makes thee give to the Poor, and deſire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter communion with God, that draws thee to hear the Word of God and to pray unto God. If it be ſo with thee, thou mayſt go home with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, for I dare warrant thee from the Word of God, that God hath loved thee with an everlaſting Love; &amp; that thou hadſt a being in the love of God before thou hadſt a being in the world; for though a wicked man may be contented to be found in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of duties, for ſuch ſelf-ends as he propoſes to himſelf; yet there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enmity in his heart againſt God, it is impoſſible he ſhould propoſe Gods glory as his main and ultimate end: Therefore if thou art brought to propoſe Gods glory as thy ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate end, it is an infallible ſign that thou art an Object of Gods Love.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Another ſign of the Love of God manifeſted to the Creature is,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42902:10"/>when we are fruitful in our places, to draw others unto Jeſus Chriſt, as well as to bring forth the fruits of an holy converſation our ſelves. After that the Spouſe had been ſetting forth the excellency of the Love of Chriſt, and had been begging a kiſſe of her beloved, ſhe was ſo taken with his love, that preſently ſhee crys out,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can</hi> 1.2, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Draw me, we will run after thee;</hi> draw me in the ſingular, we in the Plural will run after thee: A perſon that has taſted of the ſweetneſs of the Love of God, waites all opportunitys to ſay with <hi>David, Come and ſee what God hath done for my ſoul:</hi> oh ſaith the ſoul, I was by nature an enemy to God, and not only ſo, but I had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in my heart againſt God; And bleſſed be his name that was pleaſed to bring down that enmity by ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding abroad his love in my heart. Thus the object of Gods Love will endeavour to bring others in Love with this lovely object the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 14. after
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42902:10"/>that God had (in the 4. <hi>verſe</hi>) mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted the freeneſs of his love to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, we may ſee in the 5. and 6. <hi>verſes,</hi> that God will be as the <hi>dew upon Iſrael,</hi> and that <hi>he ſhall grow as the lilly, and caſt forth his roots as Lebanon,</hi> by which is meant nothing elſe but the fruitfulneſs of it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That Soul that hath the Love of God ſhed abroad in it is inſatiably deſirous of more of it; a <hi>David</hi> that hath taſted the ſweetneſs of the Love of God, he can in a ſenſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of cry out,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6.4.51.8</note> 
               <hi>Lord lift thou the light of thy countenance upon me,</hi> and Lord, <hi>reſtore unto me the Joy of thy Salvation.</hi> It is reported of the Lyoneſs, that when ſhe hath once taſted of mans fleſh, ſhe will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſatisfied without more of it: &amp; when a Soul has once taſted of the ſweetneſs of the Love of the lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> by feeding upon his fleſh by Faith; he will never be ſatisfied without more of it. Now if God ſhould put them to their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42902:11"/>choice (as he did <hi>Solomon</hi>) and ask ſuch, whether they would have the ſhinings in of Gods countenance, or the pleaſures of ſin: Oh, ſay, ſuch Souls, <hi>Give us the ſweetneſs of thy love in Chriſt!</hi> But ſuppoſe a Soul be asked, whether it would have the Love of God or the pleaſures and profits of the World; oh ſaith the Soul, the profits and pleaſures of the world, are but gliſtering vanities, that are empty of what they promiſe, and inticeing with what they have; and God can quickly take the world from me or me from the world: But if I have once the love of God I ſhall enjoy it for ever: for, <hi>neither death nor life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 38, 39</note> 
               <hi>nor Angels nor Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor highth, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſeparate me from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi> Now my friends, I pray ſee whether you have theſe ſharp appetites after more of the love of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42902:11"/>God, then it is indeed ſign that you are objects of the love of God; a true Believer that has taſted the ſweetneſs of the love of God, is ready to ſay as <hi>Rachel</hi> did in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe, <hi>Give me Children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 30.1.</note> 
               <hi>or elſe I dye;</hi> ſo ſaith the Soul, give me more of the love of God, or elſe my life will be a burden to me. Oh ſaith the ſoul, I am compaſſed about like <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> with <hi>Moab, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and mount <hi>Seir;</hi> ſin, the world &amp; the Devil; the father torments my Spirit, and the children my fleſh; and being now in this deplorable ſtate, if God will not revive my ſoul with the ſweet cordials of his Love, what comfort can I have in my life? Now if thou art thus breathing after more of the love of God, it is a ſign thou haſt it already, or elſe thou wouldſt prefer any thing before it: but if on the contrary thou canſt with <hi>Herod</hi> prefer an <hi>Herodias;</hi> ſinful pleaſure before the love of God; and with
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42902:12"/>
               <hi>Saul,</hi> prefer the love of the people of the world, before the love of God; or with <hi>Demas,</hi> prefer the profits of the world before the love of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.9. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.30. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10.</note> it is a ſign thou never yet haſt had it ſhed abroad in thy heart.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Wouldſt thou know whether thou canſt aſſure thy ſelf of the love of God, then ſee whether God doth exerciſe thee with Afflictions, and ſanctify afflictions unto thee; as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanctified Proſperity is no certain ſign of the love of God, ſo neither are unſanctified Afflictions; for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haz</hi> was under great afflictions, and yet an object of Gods hatred, <hi>and</hi> God is pleaſed to Stigmatize him to the world,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron</hi> 28.22.</note> to be <hi>that King Ahaz.</hi> In which God does as it were point with the finger, ſaying, this is that incorrigible wretch that would not be wrought upon by Afflictions. But if thou art exerciſed with Afflictions; and thoſe thou art exerciſed with draw thee nearer unto God, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42902:12"/>make thee mourn that thou ſhouldſt provoke thy loving-tender-hearted father, to lay ſuch ſtrokes upon thy back; and that if thou wert put to thy choice thou hadſt rather be rid of thy Sin, than of thy afflictions and not be rid of thy ſins alſo; it is a ſign that thou art an object of Gods love; This is cleared up from the 3 of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> compared with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>In the Revelations,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are made a ſign of Gods love, <hi>thoſe whom I love I rebuke and chaſten,</hi> in that 94 <hi>Pſal.</hi> we may ſee, when afflictions are ſigns of Gods love, and that is, when they are teaching Afflictions; when in Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions God teacheth us to know the evil of ſin, in its curſed nature, which is the meritorious cauſe of all Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: In a word, when Afflictions are ſo ſanctified as to make us love God more, hate Sin more, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenm the world more, and to deſire to lye down patiently under the hand
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42902:13"/>and will of God, and ſay with <hi>Ely, it is the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>let him do what ſeemeth good in his ſight;</hi> and with <hi>Hezekiah Good is the word of the Lord;</hi> good is this affliction from the hand of my good God, and that it is the grief of thy ſoul, when thou doeſt find a contumacious will, thwarting the will of God, and this reluctancy in thy will to ſubmit to the will of God under afflicting providences is thy burden; then I ſay it is a good ſign, nay, an infallible ſign, that God doth exerciſe thee with thoſe afflictions in love to thy precious Soul. Indeed it is too ordinary for Gods people, yea his beloved ones, to look upon Afflictions as ſigns of Gods anger; but though it be ſo with ſome, yet it is not ſo with all. I knew a gracious woman in <hi>Cambridge</hi> was wont to ſay, that if God ſhould not be pleaſed ſometimes to afflict her, ſhe ſhould fear he had forgot her: and truly, I think, if there were more of this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42902:13"/>gracious ſubmiſſive frame of Spirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians, in making a right conſtruction of the dealings of God towards them, it would put a period to thoſe murmurings &amp; complaints, and that uncomfortable deportment that doth ſo much predominate even in Gods beloved ones when they are under Afflictions.</p>
            <p n="7">7. If thou wouldſt know whether thou art an object of Gods love, then ſee if God doth give thee Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with himſelf in dutys; an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Gods hatred may injoy the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God; but only true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers can injoy Communion with the God of Ordinances. Can. 2.4. <hi>The Spouſe tells us, that when her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved brought her into the banquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting houſe his banner over her was love;</hi> which in the original is the houſe of wines, and is therefore very fitly tranſlated banquetting, becauſe wine is frequently uſed at banquetting: and that which is comprehended in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42902:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>the words is mainly this, that when believers are found diligently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending on the means of grace, God will at one time or other, in one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or other, manifeſt himſelf and his love towards them. The world is compared to a ſea, and Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the world are like the diſciples on the ſea, toſſed with the waves of afflictions and temptations, and Chriſt apppears to them ſpiritually as he did to the diſciples corporally, but they are ready to cry out as the diſciples did, it is a Spirit; oh ſaith a Soul, I had a little comfort in ſuch an ordinance, but I am affraid it is but a Spirit, deluſion; but at length Chriſt ſpeaks ſo powerfully to the Soul, by the operations of his holy Spirit, that the Soul knows it to be the voice of Chriſt. And then with the diſciples it gladly receives Chriſt into its Soul, and when Chriſt doeth thus commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate himſelf, he doeth then mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt his endeared affection to it: oh
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42902:14"/>but methinks, I hear ſome poor Soul ready to ſay, truly here is but little comfort for me, for if Gods communicating himſelf to a Soul in the manner you have been ſpeaking be a ſign of Gods love, then God help me, my caſe is bad enough, for I do not find ſuch communications of the graces and comforts of the Spirit to my Soul. God knows I come time after time to hear the word, and I go to prayer, and I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, but I come with a dead heart and a dull Spirit, and ſo I go away a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and have none of thoſe quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning influences of the Spirit reviv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and refreſhing of my Soul. God doth not make me joyful in his houſe of prayer, which makes me fear that I am none of thoſe whom God loves. Poor Soul, doeſt thou utter this mournful language, in a formal complementing way, or is it the language of a <hi>Nathaniel?</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:42902:15"/>doth it proceed really from thy heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then take this for thy comfort and carry it home with thee, and let it be as a cordial to revive thy poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> drooping Spirits. That God hath already communicated himſelf to thy Soul: or elſe thou wouldſt neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deſire after communion with him in duty. As a wicked earthly minded <hi>Ahab</hi> (having never ſo much of the earth) is ſick with vexation of Spirit, for want of <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard; ſo a Godly, Heavenly, Heaven born Saint (though it doth injoy communion with God) it is diſſatisfied, becauſe it thinks it hath not ſo much as others: a ſtone caſt up into the air will never reſt till it comes to the earth which is its center, ſo God being the center of a gracious Soul, it is reſtleſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out communion with him, but on the contrary, if thou canſt go from one duty to another and ſit down ſatisfied with the bare performance of the duty; and yet art flattering thy
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42902:15"/>ſelf that thou art an object of Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove; I tell thee thou art but feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the eaſt wind, and carrying lye in thy right hand, for there are one that can aſſure themſelves of he love of God, but they have ſuch Revelation of God to their Souls, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s doth fill them with Heavenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oys: Or make them be diſſatisfied without thoſe comfortable diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>es of God to their Souls.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Wouldſt thou be aſſured of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he love of God through a ſuffering Chriſt, then ſee if God hath given <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee an heart to deſire to ſuffer for Chriſt: when Chriſt hath helped the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oul by an eye of ſaith, to ſee what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat things he'l ſuffer for his ſake, doth as the Apoſtle ſays, conſtrein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſoul to expoſe it ſelf, to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reateſt ſufferings for the cauſe of God, when he ſhall be pleaſed to all him to it. When the love of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omes to be ſhed abroad, in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eart by the holy Ghoſt, it will make
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42902:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>a Soul ſay (with <hi>Paul</hi>) that it glorieth in tribulation; when the Soul comes to be inflamed with the love of God, many waters of affliction from God, nor floods of perſecutions from men cannot drown it: oh ſaith the ſoul, how can I ſhew my love enough to God, that hath ſhewed ſo much love to me? But on the contrary, if thou art one that will ſuffer nothing for God, thou canſt not upon any ſure grounds aſſure thy ſelf, that Chriſt hath ſuffered any thing for thee to purchaſe the love of God.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Wouldſt thou know thy inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the love of God, then ſee if thou doeſt hate ſin. For it is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent, for the Revelation of Gods love to the ſoul, and the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſouls love to ſin, to be in the ſoul at one and the ſame time: nothing gives ſuch a mortal wound to ſin, nor makes it bleed to death ſooner, in the ſoul, than the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the love of a wounded
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42902:16"/>Saviour that did bleed for the ſoul. My Friends, you may take this for a certain truth, that propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably to the love of God that is manifeſted unto you, ſuch will be your hatred of ſin that you commit againſt God, as a woman that hath experienced much of her husbands love, it makes her violent againſt her husbands enemies, ſo a believer having experienced much of the love of God, ſets his ſoul the more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin which he knows is Gods greateſt enemy: oh ſaith the Soul (that hath the love of God ſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in it) how can I hug this ſin in my boſome that did pierce my dear and loving Lord Jeſus to the heart, how can I hide this ſin as ſugar under my tongue, which did cauſe the ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue of my Lord Jeſus to utter thoſe bitter cryes, and heart rending ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, with his eyes full of tears, and his heart full of lamentations; <hi>My God
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42902:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>my God why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> when God hath once diſcovered the freeneſs of his Love unto his people, they quickly ſay with <hi>Ephraim, what have I to do any more with Idols?</hi> but if on the contrary thou loveſt and delighteſt in ſin, and art ready to extenuate it, it is a ſign that the love of God is not ſhed abroad in thy Soul.</p>
            <p n="10">10. If thou art one that canſt really experience the love of God in and to thy Soul, thou art not only brought to hate ſin, becauſe it is ſuch an enemy to that God who hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted ſo much love to thy Soul, but God hath really deſtroyed Sin in thy Soul, it being thine enemy as well as his. I ſhall endeavour to ſet it forth by a ſimilitude, and how God doth manifeſt his love to his people by deſtroying their corruption, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a man were walking on the way with his wife, and ſhe ſtraying out of the way ſhould be ſurprized
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42902:17"/>by a company of bloody cut-throats, and having took away or defaced her ornaments they ſhould go about to murther her; now though her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band could ſtand ſtill awhile and ſee his wife ſomewhat roughly handled, (that ſhe might take heed another time how ſhe ſtrayed ſo far from him) yet when he ſees them about to murther her, then his bowells yern towards her, and though ſhe were in a fault yet ſtill ſhe was his wife, whereupon he goes to her reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue, deſtroyes thoſe enemies of hers which otherwiſe would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed her; and thus he ſhews his love to his wife. Truly my friends thus it is, a true believer hath God for his husband, while we are in this world, we are walking on the way to heaven injoying the preſence of our heavenly busband; but the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements of the fleſh and the world are apt to draw us aſide out of the way (when we are off from our
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42902:18"/>watch). And preſently we (like <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>) are ſurprized with ſins and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh luſts, which do quickly rob us of our comforts, making us to ſtand in need (with <hi>David</hi>) to cry, <hi>Reſtore unto us the joy of thy Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation:</hi> and God ſeemes to take but little notice of us, but when our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual enemies ſhall go about to take away our ſpiritual life (for it is in the nature of predominating cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, that it would in time eat out the very life and power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs) and ſo to expoſe us to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal death. Then is the time for our Spiritual husband to ſhew his love to his poor ſpouſe, in deſtroying thoſe enemies; and thou that canſt aſſure thy ſelf of the love of God, thou rejoyceſt more when God doth manifeſt his love in deſtroying thy corruptions than in all outward in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments whatſoever. But if on the contrary thy corruptions grow and thrive as much as ever, thou haſt no
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42902:18"/>ground to aſſure thy ſelf that God loves thee. When Chriſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted his love to his ſpouſe in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageing of her to duty, Cant. 2.14, 15. <hi>Oh thou that art in the clifts of the rock, in the ſecret places of the ſtaires, let me hear thy voice, let me ſee thy countenance, for ſweet is thy voice, and thy countenance is comely.</hi> Pray mind what follows, <hi>Take us thoſe foxes, thoſe little foxes which corrupt the vines or ſpoyle the vines, for our vines have tender grapes:</hi> by thoſe foxes we underſtand as well ſin in the heart as heretick in the Church; which ſins the ſoul re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth in the deſtructions of, which have got an evidence of Gods Love.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Another ſign of our intereſt in the love of God is, if we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſpiritual life from the God of life and love; this we may ſee in the 16 of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> comparing the 6. <hi>verſe</hi> with the 8. In the 8. <hi>verſe</hi> we have
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42902:19"/>the impulſive cauſe of our ſpiritual life, &amp; that is the love of God, <hi>thy time was the time of love.</hi> In the 6. <hi>verſe</hi> we have the effect of the Love of God towards us, and this is ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al life, <hi>I ſay unto thee live.</hi> So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the 2 <hi>Gal.</hi> 20. ſee how the Apoſtle makes out his intereſt in the love of God; ſaith he (ſpeaking of his ſpiritual life) <hi>I live, yet not I, but Chriſt that liveth in me; and the life that I now live is by the faith of the Son of God who loved me and gave himſelf for me.</hi> Now my friends I beſeech you draw out your hearts before the Lord, and deal faithfully with your own ſouls, and ſee whether you can ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi> that the life that you now live is by the faith of the Son of God; then indeed you may comfortably read on the <hi>verſe</hi> and ſay, <hi>who loved me, and gave himſelf for me;</hi> till we have received ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual life from Chriſt, we can never aſſure our ſelves of the love of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42902:19"/>Chriſt, nor any benefit by the death of Chriſt. And ſo in the 2 of the <hi>Epheſ.</hi> we may ſee, that our ſpiritual life is an effect of the great love of God toward us in Jeſus Chriſt. Saith the Apoſtle in the 4. verſe, <hi>According to the great love where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hath loved us.</hi> In verſe the 5. <hi>Even when we were dead in ſins hath he quickned us together with Chriſt.</hi> Now let us ſee whether the Spirit of life in Chriſt hath made us free from the law of ſin and death. Now we know that the difference between a dead man and a living man is this; A dead man hath not his uſe of his ſenſes, (as hearing, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, feeling, taſting, ſmelling) but a living man hath the uſe of all or ſome of them. Now ſoul, wouldſt thou read the love of God in thy ſpiritual life, then ſee whether thou haſt thy ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual eye-ſight; hath God anointed thy eyes with ſpiritual eye-ſalve, and made thee ſee in ſome meaſure the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:42902:20"/>beauty of holineſs and the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Chriſt, the worth of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, the vanity of the world and the loathſomneſs of Sin, ſo as to loath thy ſelf for Sin. now as dead men haveing no ſight, can ſee no more beauty or brightneſs in the Sun, than in a dunghill; ſo a Perſon dead in treſpaſſes and ſins can ſee, nor Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Splendor, Beauty, or Luſtre, in the Sun of Righteouſneſs. But if thou art one that canſt experience the love of God in raiſing thee from the death of ſin to the life of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, thou canſt no longer ſay (with the daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) <hi>What is thy beloved more than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beloved;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.</note> but thou wilt be ready to ſay (with the daughters of <hi>Sion</hi>) <hi>my beloved is white and Ruddy the cheifeſt of ten thouſand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10.</note> And as this ſpiritual life doth convince a man of the Excellency of Chriſt, ſo likewiſe of the uglineſs of Sin: Now ſoul, ſee if thou haſt this ſpiritual feeling: we
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42902:20"/>know that as a dead man cannot ſee ſo he cannot feel; though you ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay a milſtone upon him he is ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of no more weight than if it were feather, but a living man is quickly ſenſible of a little weight: ſo is it with one ſpiritually dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, he feels no weight in his Sins though they be heavier than the whole creation, though ſin be ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy that it is a burden to God, good an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, &amp; good Men, &amp; wicked Angels, and the whole creation; yet a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man that is ſpiritually dead feels no weight therein: but if thou haſt this ſpiritual life thou art made ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the burden of Sin, whether in action, in thought, or in word, and thou haſt much trouble upon thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit for thoſe ſins, which a wicked man would make nothing of; and if it be ſo with thee, then go home with comfort, thou art one that mayſt ſay that God hath loved thee with an everlaſting love and that God hath
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42902:21"/>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted his love to thee in raiſing thee from the death of ſin to the life of righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p n="12">12. And laſtly, wouldſt thou know whether thou art an object of Gods love? then ſee if God be the higheſt object of thy love, for though Gods love to us do not flow from our love to God (for ſaith <hi>John,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>John.</hi> 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>we love him becauſe he firſt loved us</hi>) yet our love to God is an infallible ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, and glorious effect of Gods love to us; for though God doth not love thee becauſe thou loveſt him, yet till thou doeſt love him thou haſt no ground to believe that he doth love thee; now in regard that Gods beloved ones are ſo ready to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their love to God as well as Gods love to them, I intend to inſiſt upon this Particular by it ſelf, and all that I ſhall ſay to it at Preſent is this, that if thou art one that loveſt God, thou doeſt love the People of God, and the ordinances of God, and wilt not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42902:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſit down ſatisfied in an ordinance, without communion with God in the ordinance, and thou haſt an impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable hatred of ſin: now my friends ſee if it be ſo with you, doth your love to God thus manifeſt it ſelf?</p>
            <p>But if it be otherwiſe with thee, inſtead of hateing ſin you love it, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of making communion with God your end in duty, you make ſelf, pride, and vain glory your end: If inſtead of letting your thoughts dwell upon God, you are dwelling upon the world and vanity; you can have but little well-grounded hopes that you love God, and conſequently that God loves you; for ſaith the Apoſtle, we love him becauſe he firſt loved us; in which words we have, firſt an effect, Secondly a cauſe; the effect is our love to God, we love him; Secondly the cauſe, God loves us: and ſaith Jeſus Chriſt the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the father, I love them that love me; we muſt not think the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42902:22"/>meaning of the holy Ghoſt in that Scripture is to make our love to God the cauſe of Gods love to us, but the evidence of it. Now my friends, I beſeech you gather up all again; and ſee whether you can experience in your own ſouls that you have a true knowledge of God and the gifts and graces of the Spirit of God, and whether this love of God doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain thee to duty: And whether thou art a fruit-baring Chriſtian, and doeſt, in the place in which God hath put thee, endeavour to bring others to God; and examine thine unſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſires after more of this love of God; and examine whither God doth ſanctify afflictions unto thee, and give thee communion with himſelf in duty; and art thou made willing to ſuffer for God, and art thou made to hate ſin; and hath God deſtroy'd thy enemies which are thy ſins: and ſee if thou haſt received ſpiritual life from God, and haſt a Sincere love
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42902:22"/>to God. Now to conclude, if thou findeſt none of theſe markes in thy ſoul of Gods love, thy caſe is ſad, I would not be in thy Condition for ten thouſand worlds: yet though I would diſcourage thee from going on in thy Sin, becauſe a conſtant perſiſting in a courſe of Sin, is a dreadful Sign of Gods hatred; yet I dare not diſcourage thee in thy at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance on the means of grace becauſe thoſe are Gods lattices through which he does flouriſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Can.</hi> 2.9. Or, as we have it tranſlated, ſhew himſelf unto poor ſouls: therefore thou that canſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience nothing of the love of God; I beſeech thee as thou tendreſt the good of thy precious and immortal ſoul, be conſtant in attending on the means of grace; thou knoweſt not how ſoon God may dart in ſuch beams of his love to thy ſoul through the thick glaſs of Goſpel ordinances, as may make thee cry
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42902:23"/>out with the ſpouſe, <hi>ſtay me with Flagons, ſtrew me a bed with Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, for I am ſick of Love.</hi> And for you that can ſay you have had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the love of God; and can ſay of a truth that Chriſt hath kiſſed you with the kiſſes of his Lips, and that his left Arm hath been under your neck, and his right Arm hath imbraced you; you that can ſay that the time was when You did ſit under the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of my beloved with great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and his fruit was ſweet to your taſt; you that can ſay, that the time was when God did flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh himſelf unto your Souls, through the Lattice, and the Sun of Righteouſneſs did ſhine upon your Tabernacle; That God did ſo manifeſt himſelf unto your Souls in all or moſt of his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, that it may be you did not know whether you were in the body or out of the body, (as
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42902:23"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) your hearts have been forewarned and affected with the preſence of God by the influence of his Spirit; Now it may be you walk in darkneſs and have no light, inſtead of that ſweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion you had with God in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; it may be there may be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but deadneſs, and dulneſs of heart, and indiſpoſition of Soul to duty; It may be inſtead of that ſhining in of Gods love unto your Souls, you may (with <hi>Job</hi>) appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend God to be your Enemy, and be ready to ſay that God doth ſet a print on your Heels and on your Feet, and ſew up your iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in a bag, and ſeal up your ſins, <hi>Job</hi> 13.24, 26, 27. you that could formerly ſay (with <hi>David</hi>) come and ſee what God hath done for my Soul, it may be, are now rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſay (with <hi>Job,</hi>) have pity upon as oh our friends, for the hand of the Lord is upon us, <hi>Job</hi> 19, 21. and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42902:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>with the Church in the <hi>Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi> Is it nothing to you all you that paſs by? Behold and ſee if there be any ſorrow like my ſorrow, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.12. which is done unto me, wherewith the Lord hath afflicted me in the day of his fierce Wrath. Oh wo is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> us, for the Day of Comfort and Conſolation is paſſing away and the ſhadows of the evening and morning are ſtretched out Now poor ſouls, you that are thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in Hell upon Earth for want o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> comfort and conſolation from Heaven, give me leave to ſpeak two or three words to you, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the reducing you to you former comfortable eſtate; yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that are thus afflicted and to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with Tempeſt, and not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted; it will be your prudenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and it doth highly concern you to take notice what wind hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brought this Tempeſt, which ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:42902:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>filled your Souls with ſuch clouds of deſpondencies: for either the Eaſt Wind of ſinful Security, or the North Wind of pinching Adverſity, or the South Wind of unſanctified Proſperity, has undoubtedly raiſed theſe ſtorms in your Souls, which for ſome time and in ſome meaſure make an interpoſition between the comfortable rayes of the Light of Gods Countenance and thy poor ſoul. For the firſt, ſee if the eaſt wind of ſinful ſecurity hath not raiſed this Tempeſt of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and deſpondency: though God doeth greatly delight to ſecure his people from the God of this world, yet his people will find but ſmall comfort in their ſinful ſecurity before God, whilſt they be in this World; though God doeth ſo watch over a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever that he ſhall never be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome by temptations, yet for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42902:25"/>want of watchfulneſs in a believer, God may ſuffer him to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to Temptation; though a true believer cannot loſe the God of comfort and conſolation, yet he may for a time loſe the comfort and conſolation of his God: if the blaſting Eaſt wind of carnal ſecurity make the ears thin and empty, no wonder if thou art not filled with the ſouth wind of comfort and conſolation; if <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> think their mountain ſo ſtrong that they ſhall not be moved, to deny the Fountain of their Comfort and Conſolation, God will moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly deny them (for a time) the Comforts from the Fountain. Again in the next place, ſee if the ſouth wind of unſanctified proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity have not blown up theſe ſtorms of ſanctifiing Adverſity; for Gods end in imbittering our beloved outward enjoyments (by
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42902:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>denying us his comforting preſence) is to make his conſolations more ſweet unto us, and us more earneſtly to labour after the enjoyment of them: when Gods beloved ones have too much delight in, and too much love to the world, ſo as to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue the heavenly manna of Gods love; then the God of love will manifeſt his delight in, and love to his people, in leaveing them (as to his comforting preſence) (with the prodigal) to ſeed upon the husks of outward injoyments, till they are brought to ſee the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity, that is between the empty, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticeing, tranſitory vanity of this World: and their ſublime and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls, which can receive no real comfort from, or any ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory delight or complacency, in any thing but what is of its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſoul of a believer meerly as it is a Creature, is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42902:26"/>ſubſtance and the very breath of God; and therefore no wonder though the creature find ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency of comfort in all outward injoyments, they being ſo much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and unſuitable to its nature. And that I take to be the reaſon why <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.13. <hi>that in the midſt of laughter the heart may be ſad;</hi> the fading, earthy, mortal body may laugh in the injoyment of fad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, earthly, momentany things, and yet the heart and ſoul may be ſad for want of ſomething of its own nature for to take delight and compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency in. Now let us draw to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion; in a word there muſt be an aſſimulation between the Object of delight, and the Subject delighting it ſelf in that object. As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, a fiſh of a cold and moyſt nature delights in the paſſive element of water, being of its own nature; But the Salamander being of a fiery na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42902:26"/>delights in the active element of fire: So a true believer, being a new creature, born of God by regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, cannot but mourn in the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his ſoul, when it does conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how the fleſhy part has prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt his Spiritual part (being off from his watch) as (with <hi>Michal</hi>) to ſend away his bleſſed King <hi>David</hi> (as to his comforting preſence) and have left nothing but an Image of outward Injoyments in the room thereof. And if Gods beloved <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> will be ſolaceing of themſelves in the laps of the deceitful <hi>Dalilahs,</hi> you can expect nothing but that thoſe ſweet Syrene-like ſongs ſhould end in the ſhipwrack of their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Joys: Having provoked God, to deliver them up (with <hi>Sampſon</hi>) to the Philiſtins, to cut off the ſeven locks of their ſpiritual ſtrength, and leave them in the hands of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual enemies, that will by (filling
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:42902:27"/>of their Souls with horror and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Spirit) do their utmoſt, to keep thoſe from heaven whilſt they live, which they ſee they cannot keep from heaven when they dye. And now I come to the <hi>North</hi> wind of affliction, which does often make Gods <hi>Davids</hi> cry out, I have cleanſed my heart in vain, and with Gods <hi>Jobs</hi> to look upon outward afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be ſigns of Gods anger and diſpleaſure; whereas indeed as well the <hi>North</hi> Wind of ſanctified af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions as the <hi>South</hi> Wind of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied proſperity blowing upon our gardens, will make our ſpices flow forth, will make us to be much in exerciſing the gifts and graces of the ſpirit of God in us. Now, ſoul, ſee which of theſe winds it is that has blown up this dreadful ſtorm in thy ſoul? if it be the <hi>Eaſt</hi> Wind of ſinful ſecurity, or the <hi>South</hi> Wind of unſanctified proſperity, or the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:42902:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>North</hi> Wind of adverſity? And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as ſin is the meritorious cauſe of affliction, ſo affliction makes a ſoul apprehend it ſelf to be a greater ſinner than others, when it is more afflicted than others. And the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil has a great hand in this, for as he perſwades the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that their proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis is a ſign of Gods love, ſo he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades Gods people, that afflictions are ſigns of Gods hatred. If the people of God did but know the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious end God has in afflicting them, they would never look upon them to be ſigns of his diſpleaſure: For Gods ends in afflicting his people are to glorify his wiſdom in their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and his holineſs in their Sanctification, and his power in their Supportation and Preſervation, and that they might be more conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Chriſt their head, and that they may hate ſin the more, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn the world the more, and long after heaven the more, and that they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42902:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>may be in the better capacities to ſympathize with Gods people in their ſuffering, when they are under the like afflictions, and to make hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the ſweeter to them, by make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the world bitter. Now ſoul, thou that art under theſe clouds, and toſſed with theſe tempeſts, and not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, be ſure to look often into the waters of the ſanctuary upon the bended knees of thy ſoul, and there thou ſhall ſee the Comet that has made the interpoſition between the ſhineing rayes of Gods love and thy poor ſoul; and when thou haſt found out this <hi>Achan</hi> that troubles the camp, that made thee flee before the men of <hi>Aie;</hi> and after thou haſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered <hi>Jericho,</hi> and by Gods mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſounding of the Goſpel-Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet beat down the walls of the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Jericho</hi> of the Kingdom of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in thy ſoul; when thou haſt found out the <hi>Achan</hi> that would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve any of the curſed thing, be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potant
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42902:28"/>with thy bleſſed <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> which brings his true <hi>Iſrael</hi> into the land of promiſe, that he would paſs the ſentence of death, on this thee viſh <hi>Achan,</hi> that firſt ſtole thy heart from the God of comfort and conſolation, and then ſtole from thee the ſweet conſolations of thy God: Oh ſoul, let not the Silver or Gold of worldly-mindedneſs which lies hid in the midſt of <hi>Achans</hi> tent, let not any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal profit that thy ſin may bring thee in, make <hi>Achan</hi> faire ever the better; but ſeek diligently for it, for it lyes hid in the midſt of the tent where it might be the leaſt ſuſpected; &amp; ſee if <hi>Achan</hi> has not been a troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to thee by ſtealing ſomething elſe beſides the wedg of Gold, ſee if he has not got a cloak of <hi>Shinar</hi> or a <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> garment of ſelf-righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</p>
            <p>My meaning is this; look diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into thy heart, ſee if thou art not ready to be prideing of thy ſelf in thy
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42902:29"/>dutys, and having had great Inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in prayer, art thou not ready to think that that duty (as it comes from thee) is more likely to find ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with God, than thoſe poor broken expreſſions of thy friend, whom it may be thou contemneſt as not having ſuch abilities, as thou haſt. Now ſoul, if thou canſt find this in thy heart, then thou mayſt ſay there is the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> garment, which the old man the unregenerate part, the curſed <hi>Achan</hi> has ſtole, and by which God was provoked againſt thee; but if thou canſt ſay of a truth upon ſerious ſelf-examination that it is otherwiſe with thee, and that thy heart doeth not condemn thee of ſtealing theſe wedges of gold, that thou haſt not an inordinate love to the world, &amp; that thou haſt not ſtole the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> garment of ſpiritual pride in duty; and through grace thou canſt ſay; that neither the <hi>Eaſt</hi> Wind of ſinful ſecurity, nor the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42902:29"/>
               <hi>South</hi> Wind of unſanctified proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, nor the North Wind of Pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing adverſity have brought theſe clouds over thy ſoul; then comfort thy ſelf with this, that it will not be long ere the Sun of righteouſneſs will diſpel thoſe thick and foggy miſts of dejection and deſpondency with the reſplendent rays of his love and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2. it will not be long before God will ſay to thy Soul, oh thou afflicted and toſſed with tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts and not comforted, behold, I <hi>will lay thy ſtones with faire colours, and thy foundations with ſaphires, Iſaiah.</hi> 54.11. it will not be long before the Lord will ſay unto thee thy <hi>maker is thy husband verſ.</hi> 5 though now thou lookeſt upon thy ſelf, to be a caſt-off and a refuſed Creature; it will not be long before God will ſay unto thee by his Spirit in his promiſes <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>though for a ſmall moment he hide his face from thee, yet with everlaſting kindneſs
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42902:30"/>will he have mercy upon thee: And</hi> though now in the extremity of thy grief, thou mayeſt ſeem to thy ſelf and others, to go on frowardly, or to turn aſide, be worſe by thy troubles, yet ſaith God, I have ſeen his ways &amp; will heal him, I will lead him alſo &amp; will reſtore comfort to him &amp; to his <hi>Mourners</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57 17, 18.</note>; &amp; though thou mayſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly think God long, &amp; ſay as <hi>Siſera's</hi> Mother did in another caſe, <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.28. <hi>Why tarry the wheels of his Chariot:</hi> yet know this for thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that when the ſeaſonableſt time is, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Thy beloved will come leaping over the Hills, and Skipping over the Mountains,</hi> in ſo much that the greateſt oppoſition ſhall not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, when the ſeaſonableſt time is for him to come with comfort to thy ſoul; therefore ſoul, wait pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, for the viſion is for an appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time, and he that ſhall come will come, and will not tarry; and Gods ends in ſtaying ſo long before he
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:42902:30"/>comes with comfort to thy ſoul, may be to make comfort ſo much the more ſweet; and welcome to thy ſoul, and to make thee the more wide and capacious veſſel, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſo much the more comfort and conſolation; and it is no ſmall ground of comfort, that God has made thee willing to wait ſo long for comfort, from a right object and in a right way: it may be a ground of comfort to thee that thou art not with <hi>Saul,</hi> ſeeking comfort from a muſical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, or going to the Devil for comfort, 1 <hi>Samuel.</hi> 16.23.28.7. Or that thou art not with <hi>Cain</hi> ſeeking comfort from riches, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.15.17. the next news you hear of <hi>Cain</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his trouble of Mind was he was building a city: it is ground of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that thou art not with <hi>Ahito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> making a halter thy comforter; and therefore comfort thy ſelf with this, that God has made thee willing to wait on him for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42902:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>in his own way; and remember therefore this ſoul, that Gods time to comfort thee is the beſt time, and howſoever thoſe various revolution<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in thy ſoul, thoſe thy many Ups and Downs, may ſeem to threaten thee with a miſerable diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy comfort, yet know this that God who takes care of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral ſparrows, will not forget hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpiritual doves: oh but it may be ſome may be ready to ſay, if I wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome eminent Chriſtian ſuch as <hi>Pete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Silas</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were, then I ſhould think that God would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern himſelf with my Condition, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I am a poor inconſiderable Creatur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſlighted by the world &amp; ſlighted by Gods people, imputing my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be nothing elſe but a pettiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> humour, and truly, I am fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful I may too truly ſay with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Church, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.14. That God hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forgotten me and doth overlook my trouble: poor ſoul take heed tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:42902:31"/>doeſt not diſhonour God, by having ſuch low and unbecoming thoughts of him, as to think that there is any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing ſo great as not to be within his power, or to be ſo ſmall as not to be within his care. Thy Creation, and Redemption, coſt God as much power and love, as the Creation and Redemption of <hi>Peter</hi> or <hi>Paul</hi> did, and God doth as much concern him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf with thy condition as if he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>othing elſe to look after; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore comfort thy ſelf with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ideration of that care and wiſedom which God doth manifeſt in all the windings and circumſtances of every Diſpenſation he orders forth unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this Diſcourſe with a word to thoſe who have had his aſſurance of the love of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſtill retain it. All that I ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay to theſe is this, be ſure that your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vidences of the love of God be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uly grounded upon the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:42902:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>trials, and not upon the injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of outward mercies, and then be found conſtant and conſcionable in the diſcharge of all thy relative and religious duties, that thou maiſt keep up in thy ſoul the freſh appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of Gods love continually; for though thou that art a belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, canſt never loſe the love of God as to the habit or being of it, yet thou maieſt loſe the love of God as to the evidence of it unto thee, and therefore Chriſt bid thoſe to whom he had diſcovered his love, to continue in his love, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith <hi>Jude</hi> keep your ſelves in the love of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object. Hoſ.</hi> 9.15. doeth not God tell his people that he would love them no more; in which words, there are two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt ſomething implied, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly. Something preſſed and propoſed; that which is implied
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:42902:32"/>is that God did love them, but that which is expreſſed is, that he would love them no more. Therefore how can you make it appear that we can never loſe the love of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We do grant that there is implied a love of God to thoſe who were no more to be the objects of his love, but what a love was it? we know God hath a general love to all his creatures, and this general love of pity extends it ſelf not only to rational creatures, but even to wicked men: God hath a love of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty even to wicked men as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9. <hi>In his love and in his pity he redeemed them,</hi> who were they that God hath ſuch a love of Pity to, we may ſee in the 10 <hi>verſ. It was ſuch as were rebels againſt him and vexed his holy Spirit,</hi> and in the <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 78 38 <hi>verſ. We may ſee that God was ſo full of compaſſion that he is ſaid to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give their iniquitys,</hi> &amp; would not ſtir up all his wrath, yet though God did extend
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:42902:33"/>ſo much pity towards them, it did manifeſt it ſelf only in externals: let us take a view of this people, that were ſuch large ſharers in this love of pity and compaſſion of God; if we look into the 8. <hi>verſ.</hi> we may ſee their Stubborneſs and Rebellion, in the 9. <hi>verſ.</hi> they turned back in the day of battel, in the 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> they break Covenant with God, and did not walk in his wayes, in the 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> they were forgetful of his goodneſs, and for many verſes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we may ſee their infidelity with the higheſt aggravation imaginable and in the 29. <hi>verſ.</hi> we may ſee their great ingratitude in abuſeing the mercys of God, firſt to eat and drink for the gratifying their luſts, and then to riſe up to play, in the 32. <hi>verſ.</hi> we may ſee their incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibleneſs and unbelief, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, God had ſuch a general compaſſion of them, and ſuch love to them, as did ingage him
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:42902:33"/>ſo to manifeſt his love towards them, as to forgive their iniquitys ſo as not to cut them off ſuddenly, and yet notwithſtanding all this pitifull love of God, extended to them in a general way, they ſtill remain ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of his wrath and abhorrency, ſo that he would neither let their bodys come into <hi>Canaan,</hi> nor their ſouls in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heaven, and this love mentioned in <hi>Hoſea</hi> is only ſuch a love as is mentioned in the 63. <hi>Iſai.</hi> and it is no more then if the Lord had ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Ephraim,</hi> I have exerciſed much patience towards thee, ever ſince <hi>Jereboam</hi> did ſet up his abominable Idolatry, I have waited to be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a long time, but now I will drive them out of my houſe I will un-church them, I will take away mine ordinances from them, they ſhall no more injoy the ordinary Symptomes of my love, to wit, thoſe ſpiritual priviledges and advantages by which I do in a general way manifeſt,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:42902:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>my love to a Nation in general, and though I dare not be poſitive in my aſſertion, I being but a man, and therefore not infallible, yet I cannot but judg this to be the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of the good ſpirit of our God, becauſe the Ordinances of Good, vouchſafed to a Nation, are in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture declared to be manifeſtations of his love. Thus having endeavoured to ſhew the meaning of the Holy Ghoſt in this Scripture, in anſwer to what might be objected (from it) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Immutability of the Love of God to believers, I ſhall draw up all to this concluſion, that though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may ſeem to be mutable, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal manifeſtations of his love to a Nation in general, yet he is immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his eternal love to every true believer in particular.</p>
            <p>And this is that which may be a ground of much conſolation to thoſe that can by what hath been ſaid, make it clear to their own ſouls, that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:42902:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>they are ſuch that God hath ſuch an everlaſting love unto, for if thou art an object of Gods everlaſting love, his Wiſdom ſhall be engaged for thy Direction: and his Power for thy Protection, and his Holineſs for thy Sanctification, and his mercy for thy Salvation, Oh my Friende, I want words to ſet forth and expreſs the thouſand part of your happineſs, that are in the love and favour of God, truly my friends, I may ſay of the love of God as <hi>David</hi> did of the City of God, glorious things are ſpoken of thee, O thou love of God, thou that artan object of Gods love, thou haſt all the Attributes of God, and the offices of Chriſt, and the influences of the Spirit all ingaged for thy San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification and Comfort and Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: the evidence of this love of God is, that which will be unto thee bread in famine, drink in drought, peace in war, health in Sickneſs, like in death: the love of God in Chriſt
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:42902:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>manifeſted to thy ſoul, is that tree which will ſweeten the waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> even the bitter waters of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: The ſenſe of this love of God is that which will lift thee up above the frowns &amp; flatteries of the world: the clear, diſcoveries of Gods love will make thee willing to ſuffer from God or for God: and to conclude all in a world, the ſenſe of Gods love will make thee live holily, and live humbly, and live thankfully, and live matchfully, and live believe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, and live comfortably, and live fruitfully, and dye joyfully, in full aſſurance of reigning gloriouſly with him who loved thee before all time, and manifeſted his everlaſting love to thee in time, injoying the fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> fruition of his love when time ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be ſwallowed up to eternity; and then there ſhall be no more ſinfull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Comets to make an interpoſition, the Sun of Righteouſnes and thy poor ſoul, but (eagle-like) thou ſhalt be
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:42902:35"/>continually above the clouds of Sin or Sufferings, and injoy in a greater meaſure, then now thou art capable, of the love of God, in as great bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſerenity, as thou wilt then be in a capacity to receive. Now to the God of love by all the objects of his love be aſcribed all Honour and Glory for ever and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
